Shavua tov everybody, today's daf is דף מד Daf Mem Daled because
of a, it's a large daf and I'm also a little pressed
for time today. We're not going to do the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, but
we'll God willing we'll get back to the ירושלמי Yerushalmi tomorrow. We
stop at the top of מד, Mem Daled, we start at the
top of מד עמוד א. Mem Daled Amud Aleph. We're dealing with
the משנה Mishnah that speaks about encouraging the person who's about to
receive the death penalty to do וידוי Viduy
and then there's a whole question of let's say he doesn't want
to do וידוי Viduy or he says, whatever we'll get to that.
But anyway, the basis for this is עכן Achan who did an
admission, a confession I should say, and then he was before he
was executed. A very powerful גמרא Gemara that says, I think it
was yesterday, right? That says יהושע Yehoshua was שיחדו בדברים, shichto bidvarim,
right? He like bribed him, he encouraged him to confess thinking he
would get off. And you know, that also suggests the implicit dynamic
here, which is that the confession is good for the soul, right?
You know, the מיתה היא כפרה mita's a kaparah and we very
much are seeing our role as a בית דין Beis Din as
sort of God's messengers and this is justice and this actually will
atone for the person and there's no question that that's a very
central part of the sort of theology here. But obviously there's another
part about like how do we בית דין Beis Din look? And
is it clear that we're doing the right thing? And is it
clear to other people that we're doing the right thing?
So and that becomes complicated if he doesn't want to confess. We
know that it's in sort of like dictatorships or now whatever, totalitarianism
governments, where they force
confessions. Why are they forcing confessions there? You know, so it exonerates
them. So חס ושלום chas v'shalom I'm not saying that here, but
I'm just saying that the idea of שיחדו בדברים shichto bidvarim is
a hard concept if the whole point was that he wanted עכן
Achan to get כפרה kaparah for himself. You know, there's a public
aspect to that where it makes it clear that everybody that the
בית דין Beis Din is acting correctly. And it also to some
degree parallels the idea by the התראה hatra'ah where you say עד
שיתיר עצמו למיתה. ad she-yatir atzmo l'mitah.
It's not enough to say I know what I'm doing is wrong
and it's חייב מיתה, chayav mitah, it sort of says על מנת
כן, al menas ken, I'm doing it on the condition of this.
So you are sort of actively the perpetrator is actively agreeing and
accepting the death penalty upon himself which also as we discussed, takes
away the whole problem about what right do we have to you
know do a violent act against another person. So part of it's
because we represent God, right? And that's the כי המשפט לאלקים. ki
hamishpat l'elokim. But part of it's also,
look, the person knew it and did it and we're just sort
of carrying out what the person himself was essentially was asking for,
you know, and willingly accepted upon himself. So anyway, I think it's
important to think about those aspects.
But yes, is death atoned for without confession?
That's an interesting question and we'll see about that. We're not done
yet with the whole confession and whatever. Okay, so with עכן Achan
anyway, we get to the top of מד עמוד א Mem Daled
Amud Aleph and it says that you know why was עכן... Achan...
whole question about was עכן Achan punished because it was,
we should be a good place to start from.
Let's I guess start from the bottom of מג עמוד ב. Mem
Gimmel Amud Bais. Okay, okay.
So the question is how many other types of חרם cherem of
similar sins did עכן Achan do? Okay so we'll just start from
the first wide line, end of the first wide line. רבי יוחנן
אמר משום רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון: Rabbi Yochanan amar mishum Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Shimon: חמישה. Chamisha. There were five other types of מעל בחרמים,
mo'al b'charamim, taking benefit from the stuff under the ban. ארבע בימי
משה, Arba b'yemei Moshe, four in the time of משה, Moshe, right
there were all these various wars that they did and some of
them were explicit that they put the property under the ban. ואחד
בימי יהושע, V'echad b'yemei Yehoshua, שנאמר: shene'emar: אנכי חטאתי וכזאת וכזאת עשיתי.
Anochi chatasi v'chazos v'chazos asisi.
So כזאת וכזאת chazos v'chazos is like the you know כזאת chazos
is double and the other כזאת chazos is two more, four plus
the one, it's the five. However you do the math, תוספות Tosafos
sort of says you could even use that to have gotten to
a higher number, but there weren't so many wars. So we couldn't
have said a higher number. Anyway, והשתא מאי טעמא לא עניש? v'hashta
mai ta'ama lo yanesh? So why only now at the time of
יהושע, Yehoshua, if he sinned in the time of משה, Moshe, why
is he only now being punished in the time of יהושע?
Yehoshua? עניש כל בני ישראל yanesh kol Bnei Yisrael like when it
seems
like רש"י Rashi seems to be saying it's everyone else, right?
That's a good point. Where's the רש"י? Rashi? מאי טעמא לא עניש
ישראל
אמעילתו כי דין השתא ריבא. mai ta'ama lo yanesh Yisrael ameilaso ki
den hash'at hariba.
Thank you very much, excellent excellent point, good correction. Right, so here
the Jewish people were punished because the people died in the battle
of העי. Ha-Ai. They were punished for collectively, right, collective punishment. Right,
so why were they not punished until now? Thank you very much
Michael, that's correct.
What is יהושע Yehoshua now... what is עכן's Achan role because he's
in there with אלעזר, Elazar, right?
The אלעזר Elazar and the משה Moshe thing? No, where's אלעזר? Elazar?
Up a few lines, what is his role in the people?
Nothing, he was just some layperson. Yeah, he was just saying what
do you mean a lot proves that I'm guilty? If it was,
if you drew lots between you and אלעזר, Elazar, one said innocent
and one said guilty, one of you would be guilty. Lot doesn't
prove anything. That was the point of the אלעזר. Elazar. Okay, anyway,
but yes, thank you Michael. Here the Jewish people suffered a collective
punishment for his sin. Why were they not punished earlier? מאי טעמא
לא איענש? Mai ta'ama lo i-anish? So it says, אמר רבי יוחנן
משום רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Elazar berabi
Shimon לפי שלא ענש על הנסתרות עד שעברו ישראל את הירדן lefi
she-lo anash al ha-nistarot ad she-avru Yisrael et ha-Yarden because they didn't
know what he did. Nobody knew he did it, so therefore they
weren't punished for hidden sins until they passed over the ירדן Yarden
and then they became obligated even for a sin that somebody else
does that they weren't aware about, that was hidden, which is a
very very strange idea but let's take a look. כתנאי, Ki-tannai, this
is a בעיא דתנאי: be-aya de-tannai: הנסתרות לה' אלהינו והנגלות לנו ולבנינו
עד עולם. Ha-nistarot l'Hashem Elokeinu veha-niglot lanu u-levaneinu ad olam.
The hidden things are for God, the public things, the known things,
those are our responsibilities. למה נקוד על לנו ולבנינו ועל העין שבעד?
Lama nakud al lanu u-levaneinu ve-al ha-ayin she-ba-ad? So if there's all
these dots over לנו ולבנינו lanu u-levaneinu and the עין ayin in
עד. ad. וללמד שלא ענש על הנסתרות עד שעברו ישראל את הירדן,
Ve-lilamed she-lo anash al ha-nistarot ad she-avru Yisrael et ha-Yarden, דברי רבי
יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. So how exactly the dots tell you exactly
this point and there's a whole רש"י תוספות Rashi Tosafot we're not
going to get into it, but basically רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
is this point that we don't have to worry about the hidden
things, that's like an עד, ad, that's like there's a limit to
that. Only on that side of the ירדן Yarden we did not
have to worry about private things, hidden things. But when we passed
over, we became obligated, right, which is very strange. There's this פסוק
pasuk that says forever, עד עולם. ad olam. No, the עד, ad,
you know, really the way, you know, תוספות Tosafot suggests reading it
is הנסתרות לה' אלהינו, ha-nistarot l'Hashem Elokeinu, skip the word והנגלות, לנו
ולבנינו Veha-niglot lanu u-levaneinu, or something like that. You take the לנו
ולבנינו lanu u-levaneinu and you move it back. Anyway, obviously it's a
strange read of the פסוק, pasuk, but he says we did become
obligated on hidden things. Now, of course, it's a very like strange
idea, right? What is the basis for collective punishment? Right? And you
could say maybe it's, you know, people wouldn't sin in private had
we done a better job as a community in terms of our
education or something. But give me a break, people are human beings,
right? You can't always tie in somebody's private sins to some negligence
on the part of the community. So it seems that it's not
about fault or blame, right? It's about this idea of a collective
unity. Once you pass over, you go from being like, you know,
a people to a nation, right? And now you are this collective
unity known as, you know, the nation of Israel, and you know,
as a collective unity you are not at fault, but you are
responsible. And that's, you know, it's I'm trying to think of like
an analogy. You know, if your kid goes ahead and breaks a
store window, you might not be to blame, but you're responsible. Now
that's because you're like in a superior position, whatever. But anyway, but
you know, as a people you are one unity, and you are
and you're going to be held accountable even if you're not to
blame. That seems to be the point and how the shift happened
after, you know, they transferred over the ירדן. Yarden. So that's what
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. אמר לו רבי נחמיה: Amar lo Rabbi
Nechemia: וכי ענש על הנסתרות לעולם? Ve-chi anash al ha-nistarot l'olam? He
can't accept that. You know, you know, that's all very nice to
speak in general metaphysical terms about a nation and a unity, but
people are dying. How could somebody die as a result of something
that they're not to blame for? Right? So והלא כבר נאמר va-halo
kvar ne-emar עד עולם. ad olam. Forever the נסתרות nistarot are not
our responsibility. אלא כשם שלא ענש על הנסתרות כך לא ענש על
עונשים שבגלוי. Ela keshem she-lo anash al ha-nistarot kach lo anash al
onashim she-ba-galui. It's the reverse. The lack of national identity
that they did not have, or once they got national identity, that's
what made them responsible on things they could prevent. Before, on the
other side of ירדן, Yarden, you want to sin, it's your business.
You know, as long as you're not bothering me, what is it
my responsibility what you do? Very individualist type of a society, right?
You know, no. So the punishment, yes, there is a communal identity,
but that's an identity of being responsible, of being responsible when you're
able to do something about it. Right? It's not this responsibility that
even if it's beyond your fault. Okay. כשם שלא ענש כך לא
ענש על עונשים שבגלוי
Keshem she-lo
anash
kach lo anash al onashim she-ba-galui עד שעברו ישראל את הירדן. ad
she-avru Yisrael et ha-Yarden. הנסתרות לה' אלהינו והנגלות לנו ולבנינו. Ha-nistarot l'Hashem
Elokeinu veha-niglot lanu u-levaneinu.
It works much better in terms of the dots. והנגלות veha-niglot, לנו
ולבנינו, lanu u-levaneinu those are dotted. והנגלות Veha-niglot weren't לנו ולבנינו, lanu
u-levaneinu, like the לנו ולבנינו lanu u-levaneinu sort of says like not
exactly. It was initially הנסתרות לה' אלהינו והנגלות. ha-nistarot l'Hashem Elokeinu veha-niglot.
You know, God, it was God's responsibility everything, it wasn't not my
responsibility what somebody else were doing. After עברו את הירדן, avru et
ha-Yarden, then it was לנו ולבנינו lanu u-levaneinu on the נגלות. niglot.
On the נגלות. niglot. So anyway, that's I think a type of
an idea that fits much more with our sense. We can accept
communal responsibility if we can do something about it. Okay. So it's
really interesting this idea of like communal or national identity. Anyway, so
according to that approach, so the גמרא Gemara says אלא עכן מאי
טעמא איענש? ela Achan mai ta-ama i-anish?
So that makes sense if, you know, that makes sense if they
were not, you know, if they were punished for the נסתרות nistarot
when they passed, when they went over the ירדן, Yarden, then we
understand why the people were punished. But if they were not punished
even when they transferred over the ירדן, Yarden, even then they're only
punished for public sins, why were they punished for what עכן Achan
did? משום דהוו ידעי ביה אשתו ובניו, Mishum de-havu yad-ei bei ishto
u-vanav, because there was a public element to it. They made it
public? Yeah, so that's very interesting. You know, but that's a question,
right? Maybe... Yes, because then they could have informed other people. That's
always this hard, you know, really challenging thing, right? You know, what
happened, you know, the whole case about one of these terrorists, right?
His son or whatever, he reported to the police, you know, one
of these, can't even remember, sadly, on this day. But anyway, you
know, so yes, if you're the family member, then you're not necessarily,
you're not the same as your father and as your, and as
your wife and as your husband. And, you know, so now there,
other people can do something about it, and they're choosing not to.
Yeah, but like isn't it חילול השם Chillul Hashem if it's like
בפרהסיא, b'farhesya, meaning like ten men?
Yeah, so that's right.
But here it seems like it was like one wife and one
kid and him.
Right. So how many people have to know about it before it
becomes the community shirking its responsibility? Right? Does a public official have
to know about it? Does it have to be something that somebody
in authority could have found out about? Right? I agree with you,
meaning, you know, I would have framed it more not necessarily about
ten, but that, you know, some people whose job it is to
have this responsibility could have found out and they didn't do their
due diligence or something, I don't know. But the גמרא Gemara has
to stretch, yes, to get there.
Yes. But we have a problem, like he was stoned, right? So
now it's like we're back tracking into that parking spot. We have
to figure out what happened, like do we have some...
Right, exactly, exactly, but it's not as Michael said correctly, it's not
even just that he was stoned. He was stoned because he sinned.
It's why did the 36 people die in the war because of
his sin? But you're right, we have to now explain it. So
we're forced to say that this makes it public. But it's a
difficult answer. Okay, let's keep on going. חטא ישראל. Chata Yisrael. So
this is from the פסוקים pesukim by עכן Achan
before, you know, before עכן Achan is singled out by the lot,
God just appears, comes to יהושע Yehoshua and says Israel has sinned.
אמר רבי אבא בר זבדא, Amar Rabbi Abba bar Zavda, אף על
פי שחטא ישראל הוא. af al pi shechata Yisrael hu. Even after
somebody has sinned, חטא ישראל. Chata Yisrael. You know, they're still a
ישראל. Yisrael. Right? You know, וישכב ראובן, Vayishkav Reuven, what is it?
וישכב את בלהה פילגש אביו ויהיו בני יעקב שנים עשר. Vayishkav et
Bilhah pilegesh aviv vayihyu b'nei Yaakov shneim asar. Right? That famous דרשה.
drasha. So even after the sin, they still are ישראל. Yisrael. Now
that's all this גמרא Gemara is saying is like a nice sort
of,
like a השקפה hashkafic point. But you know, people I'm sure have
all heard this line growing up, you know, about like אף על
פי שחטא ישראל הוא, af al pi shechata Yisrael hu, no matter
how much somebody sins, that doesn't, they still have their Jewish identity
as like a הלכה halachic point. Somebody could do all the sins
under the sun, they could even convert to another religion, and that
doesn't change the fact that על פי הלכה al pi halacha they're
still considered Jewish. Well, they're also responsible. Well, they're also responsible. Okay,
that is in no גמרא. Gemara. That was, if I remember correctly,
the first person to use what, to say that was רש״י Rashi
in a תשובה teshuva who is dealing with somebody who committed apostasy,
right, converted to Christianity, and he had to make a claim about
that this person still has Jewish status and used this אגדתא agadic
גמרא Gemara to make that הלכה halachic claim. Okay, so now in
a certain way he wasn't מחדש mechadesh anything because there's no basis
in anywhere in ש״ס Shas to say that any degree of sin
removes your Jewish identity. You know, you'd have to make the argument
the other way. But nevertheless, it was a very powerful rhetorical point,
right, to say that, you know, to use this גמרא Gemara to
make that הלכה halachic claim, that no matter how a person sins,
it does not affect their Jewish identity. Okay, so that's all in
this one little line of גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi
Abba, is
this the source?
Yeah, this is, well, it's not the הלכה, halacha, it's the source
that רש״י Rashi used to make that claim, you know, either rhetorically
or הלכה halachically to make that claim.
If a person rejects their Jewishness...
Right, so there's, well, so there was a case many decades ago
in Israel called the Brother Daniel case about somebody who had become
a monk and he wanted to come back in the Law of
Return and הרב ליכטנשטיין, Rav Lichtenstein, אהרן ליכטנשטיין Aharon Lichtenstein wrote an
article called, like on that issue about this question about like, is
there a point of where actually some status change occurs? Because some
גאונים Geonim also said that if somebody commits apostasy and converts to
another religion, when they come back, they have to go through a
גירות geirus process. Now, you know, so wanting to sort of say
maybe there are two dimensions to a person's Jewish identity and one
you lose and one you don't. Anyway, for another time. Okay.
אמר רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi Abba, yes. אמר רבי אבא היינו דאמרי
אינשי, Amar Rabbi Abba hainu d'amri inshi, that's what people say, אסא
דקאי ביני חילפי, asa d'kai beini chilfei, if you have a הדס
hadas that's growing between these thorn bushes, אסא שמיה, asa shemei, it's
still called a הדס, hadas, you know, no matter how much its
ugly surroundings. Of course, it's not exactly a good comparison because the
הדס hadas hasn't changed, it's just its surroundings have changed. Here the
actual person has sinned. But anyway, you know, the נשמה. neshama.
Oh, the נשמה, neshama, nice! Like the נשמה, neshama, the outer shell
is has been corrupted, but the נשמה neshama buried inside. Oh good.
The פינטל'ה ייד. pintele Yid. כח. Koach.
Okay. Okay. ואסא שמיה ואסא קרו ליה. V'asa shemei v'asa karu lei.
And people still call it. Meaning, you could just say not, it's
not just like objectively it's there, it's that, but you know, everybody,
its public identity is different. No, its public identity remains the same.
Okay, keeping on going. וגם עברו את בריתי אשר צויתי אותם גם
לקחו מן החרם גם גנבו וגם כחשו וגם שמו בכליהם. V'gam avru
et briti asher tziviti otam gam lakchu min hacharem gam ganvu v'gam
kichashu v'gam samu vichleihem. Okay, so this is God informing יהושע Yehoshua
*Yehoshua* of the sin and now before עכן Achan, *Achan* is sort
of found and found out through the through the גורל *Goral*. אמר
רבי *Amar Rabi*... so that's a lot of גם *gam*s there. אמר
רבי אילעא משום רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda בר מספרתא *Amar Rabi Ila
mishum Rabi Yehuda bar Masparta*, מלמד שעבר עכן Achan על חמישה חומשי
תורה Torah *melamed she'avar Achan al chamisha chumshei Torah*. Now we have
to again sort of like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s penchant to make
every רשע *rasha* the worst רשע *rasha* possible. Right? So עכן Achan
*Achan*, he transgressed all the five books of the תורה Torah. *Torah*,
שנאמר *shene'emar* חמישה גם *chamisha gam*, it says גם *gam* five times
to tell you that he committed every single sin imaginable. ואמר רבי
אילעא משום רבי יהודה בר מספרתא *Ve'amar Rabi Ila mishum Rabi Yehuda
bar Masparta*, עכן מושך בערלתו היה *Achan moshach be'orlaso hayah*. Just to
be clear now this not only about sin, but something about Jewish
identity, right? He tried to reverse his ברית מילה *bris milah*. כתיב
הכא וגם עברו את בריתי *Kasiv hacha vegam avru es brisi*, כתיב
התם את בריתי הפר *kasiv hasam es brisi heifar*. So בריתי *brisi*
is a code word for ברית מילה *bris milah*. פשיטא *Peshita*? Obviously
if he transgressed all תרי"ג מצוות *taryag mitzvos*. Of course that isn't
exactly a תרי"ג מצווה *taryag mitzvah* to reverse, but anyway. פשיטא *Peshita*?
No, מהו דתימא במצווה גופה לא פקר *mahu de'seima bemitzvah gufei lo
pakar*, he would not actually, maybe he did things about his actions,
but he wouldn't do something about his very body and
identity, קא משמע לן *ka mashma lan*
even
that he did. וכי עשה נבלה בישראל *Vechas'av nevalah beYisrael*, he did
this abomination. אמר רבי אבא בר זבדה *Amar Rabi Abba bar Zavda*,
מלמד שבא עכן על נערה המאורסה *melamed sheba Achan al na'arah hame'orasah*.
He even had intercourse with a נערה המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah*. כתיב הכא
וכי עשה נבלה *Kasiv hacha vechas'av nevalah*, כתיב התם כי עשה נבלה
בישראל *kasiv hasam ki asah nevalah beYisrael*. Okay,
so פשיטא *peshita*? Of course that's one of the תרי"ג מצוות *taryag
mitzvos*. No, מהו דתימא כולי האי לא פקר נפשיה *mahu de'seima kulei
hai lo pakar nasei*, that's already going overboard. Why is it going
overboard? I think רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says because you also make her
אסור *assur* to her husband, so you're actually hurting somebody else. Of
course the other עבירות *aveiros* hurt people like killing people. Anyway, קא
משמע לן *ka mashma lan*, even that one. רבינא אמר דיני כנערה
המאורסה *Ravina amar dinei k'na'arah hame'orasah*. No, what the point of the
comparison is to say he suffered the same punishment, the סקילה skila?
*sekilah*. The same way a נערה המאורסה *na'arah hame'orasah* who sins gets
סקילה *sekilah*, he got סקילה *sekilah*. אמר ליה amar lei ריש גלותא
לרב הונא *Amar leh Reish Galusa le'Rav Huna*. ריש גלותא *Reish Galusa*
said to רב הונא *Rav Huna*, כתיב *kasiv*, it says, ויקח יהושע
Yehoshua את עכן בן זרח ואת הכסף ואת האדרת ואת לשון הזהב
*vayikach Yehoshua es Achan ben Zerach ve'es hakesef ve'es ha'aderes ve'es leshon
hazahav*. He took him and he took the silver and this was
I think the stuff that he was מעל בחרם *mo'el b'cherem* and
the whatever the what's the אדרת *aderes*? The cloak and the string
of silver, of gold. את בניו ואת בנותיו ואת שורו ואת חמורו
ואת צאנו ואת אהלו ואת כל אשר לו *Es banav ve'es benosav
ve'es shoro ve'achamoro ve'es tzono ve'es oholo ve'es kol asher lo*. And
he killed them all. Okay, so it's going a little overboard, right?
Because what did he say? That's what he said. אם Im, הוא
חטא בניו ובנותיו מה חטאו *Im hu chata, banav uvenosav meh chatu*?
Why are again we're back to collective punishment? So even when the
individual is being sinned, why is it the here it's not just
like God's justice, it's the justice we're meeting out, why is that
being extended? Maybe again the collective
responsibility, the 36 people died we dealt with. But now here's a
בית דין beit din, *beis din*, what about for us to punish
people? There it's איש בחטאו יומתו *ish becheto yumusu* as a בית
דין *beis din*.
Why are we...
לא יומתו אבות על בנים *lo yumsu avos al banim*, right? Again,
that's God. How can we as a בית דין *beis din* punish
בניו ובנותיו *banav uvenosav*?
But his wife isn't mentioned.
Okay, and here it does. No, so it says בניו ובנותיו *banav
uvenosav*. Yeah, but his wife. I don't know, anyway. מה חטאו *Mah
chatu*? אמר ליה *Amar leh*, he said to him, ולטעמיך *u'leta'ameich* אם
הוא חטא כל שלו מה חטאו *im hu chata kol she'lo meh
chatu*? דכתיב dichtiv וכל אשר עמו *D'chasiv vechol asher immo*. Okay, but
we're back to the earlier question. So what did the rest of
the Jewish people sin? So he says is this going back on
the what do you call
it?
Yeah, but is that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* about I think that's just
that they went to I think that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* isn't that
they were punished, but I think that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is I
have to check the context. I think that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is
that they were present at his execution if I'm remembering correctly. What?
It says they were present at his execution.
I mean they're saying that he brought them there.
He brought them there to see the execution, right. So it's not
exactly מה חטאו *mah chatu* but why were if it's just about
punishing him, why was it being done in the presence of the
Jewish people? אלא לרדותם ela lirdosam *Ela lirdosam*, in order to beat
them down, which means in order to send them a clear message.
It was being done on behalf of the public good, so nobody
else should do anything like this and that's why it was a
public execution that they should all learn the message. Sort of like
the סוטה *sotah* that it's done in public and other types of
things actually coming up in this week's פרשה *parsha*. It's to teach
everybody else a lesson. So once that's true, let me just finish.
Once that's true, so it says אלא לרדותם ela lirdosam *ela lirdosam*
so הכא נמי *hacha nami* כדי לרדותם k'dei lirdosam *kedei lirdosam*. You're
right. The property and his sons and his daughters, they didn't deserve
to be killed. But they had to be killed so that everybody
else would learn this lesson. Now of course that's taking an innocent
life, but actually it's very interesting because in this coming this week's
פרשה *parsha* we have a couple of people who are punished that
goes outside of a true sense of what we would think as
a, you know, a just punishment for the crime. You have the
זקן ממרא, zaken mamre he teaches against the סנהדרין, sanhedrin, he’s put
to death, the עדים זוממים edim zomemim are put to death, the,
I think the, you know, the, what do you call it,
the, the בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh is put to death,
right? He’s not, you know, what did he do? He did like
nothing. And I think the other one, if I remember correctly, is
the נביא שקר. navi sheker. So, the question is, so, no, so
maybe שקר sheker maybe you could understand. But anyway, but okay, so
what did they, why is that a just punishment? So רמב"ן Ramban
points out as by all four of those, it
says וכל ישראל ישמעו וייראו. v'chol Yisrael yishme'u v'yira'u. And what the
פסוק pasuk. is actually saying is, you're right, here the punishment exceeds
the crime, but it's important, you know, everybody’s got to learn a
lesson. You have to protect these institutions of authority. You know, the
עדים edim is the whole institution of the court, the זקן ממרא
is the institution of like the בית דין, you know, the, you
know, חז"ל Chazal and whatever, the, whatever, חז"ל Chazal retroactively, but anyway,
the role of interpreting the תורה or the authority of interpretation of
the תורה. בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh is the parents, you
know, parental authority. So, you know, the נביא שקר navi sheker is
God’s authority. So, yeah, sometimes we're going to punish people out of
proportion in order for, you know, because וכל ישראל ישמעו וייראו. v'chol
Yisrael yishme'u v'yira'u. So that's sort of what it's saying. Yeah, I
mean, can I identify with that? Does that, you know, no, obviously
I really, still, like what, are innocent people losing their lives? But
that's very much in, fitting with a certain type of an ethos.
Yes.
How would you set that into the larger kind of, I don't
know, goal of things like, for example, minimizing
the instances when we're allowed to strike?
Right, you know, so it's good. Like, I mean, here we're interpreting
biblical verses, but then the question is which one of those serves
as models and which one of those doesn't serve as models? Yeah,
so you might be right. Like this, so first of all, we
have a, we have to explain this. I would sort of say
the other way, because the whole מסכת masechet is so much about
just punishment or whatever, we have to, we can't ignore these פסוקים.
psukim. But you're right, once we've explained it, now maybe getting that
ethos should get incorporated, right? And the powerful thing is that it
doesn't, right? You know, but you're right, like that's a really good
point.
And then רש"י Rashi takes the thing about חטאי ישראל chetei Yisrael
and not...
right, so it’s a question of which one serves as the precedent.
Exactly.
What does אלא לרדותם lirdosam, or הכי נמי hacha nami כדי לרדותם
lirdosam mean? לרדותם, is it they weren't killed or they were...?
No, לרדותם in order to beat down the rest of כל ישראל,
Klal Yisrael, in order that וכל ישראל ישמעו וייראו, v'chol Yisrael yishme'u
v'yira'u, we’re going to have to kill some innocent people.
So אלא לרדותם means לרדות את ישראל? lirdot et Yisrael? Yes. So
when it says הכי נמי hacha nami then, הכי נמי hacha nami
the same way they were the ישראל Yisrael were present in order
that the ישראל Yisrael should get this, should get a message, we
killed בנו ובנותיו bano u'vnotav in order that ישראל Yisrael should get
this message. Okay.
וישרפו אותם באש ויסקלו אותם באבנים. v'yisrefu otam ba'esh v'yisk'lu otam ba'avanim.
They burnt them in a
fire and
they stoned them. בתרתי? b'tarti? Both? I mean, come on, you get,
you're dead after the first one and which punishment is
it, שריפה sreifa or סקילה? אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, הראוי לשריפה שריפה
הראוי לסקילה סקילה. hara'uy l'sreifa sreifa hara'uy l'skila skila. Things that had
to be
burned, like
the
property, was burned. Things that should have been stoned, like the people
for the sin and certainly עכן, were stoned. Okay. ואראה בשלל, va'ere
b'shalal, now we're back to
עכן's confession. אדרת שנער אחת טובה, aderet shinar achat tova, I saw
in
there a cloak from Shinar, one good one,
ומאתים שקלים כסף, u'matayim shekalim kesef, 200 shekels of silver. רב אמר,
Rav amar,
איצטלא דמילתא, itztala d'milta, it was a cloak
of silk. ושמואל אמר, u'Shmuel amar, סרבלא דצריפא, sarvla d'tzrifa,
it was some type of a heavier cloak of, רש"י Rashi I
think says, fine wool or something, or רש"י Rashi no, actually some
type of a dyed wool. Okay. ויציקום לפני ה', v'yatzikum lifnei Hashem,
and he poured out the stuff that he had stolen, he poured
it out before God. But it's a funny word, להציק l'hatzik is
a word like used for pouring out a liquid. He didn't say
he like placed it before God. So אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav
Nachman,
בא וחבטם לפני המקום, ba v'chavtam lifnei HaMakom, he went and he
like slammed them down in front of God. אמר לפניו, Amar lifanav,
ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel Olam, and actually excuse me, and this
is now we're sort of saying יהושע Yehoshua did this, okay? I
think in the פסוק pasuk it's like עכן did this, but now
we're sort of saying יהושע Yehoshua did this.
Okay. אמר לפניו, Amar lifanav, ריבונו של עולם. Ribono shel Olam. Right,
it's so God so יהושע Yehoshua challenged God.
דכתיב ויקו מהם אנשי העי כשלושים וששה איש. vayaku meihem anshei ha'Ai
kishloshim v'shisha ish. Okay so that's רובה של סנהדרין. ruba shel Sanhedrin.
ותניא v'tanya שלושים וששה. shloshim v'shisha. It's by the way also,
you know, to go back to the point about like collective punishment
and the whole thing is about minimizing the death penalty. Often, you
know, the גמרא Gemara gives voice to the things that it's sort
of that it's challenged by
through characters in the story. So יהושע Yehoshua challenging God, you know,
is also a vehicle for חז"ל Chazal to be saying, what? Like
okay we just explained it all wonderful. They were they, you know,
they were responsible for hidden things, whatever, we're done so. Okay we're
still bothered. Like this, for this thirty-six people had to die. So
that's what יהושע Yehoshua is saying but, you know, it's also what
חז"ל Chazal are saying through this story.
Okay. What?
Not thirty-six, but what is the כ? kaf?
We're going to say that exactly right now.
Okay. ותניא v'tanya we talk in ברייתא braita שלושים וששה איש ממש
דברי רבי יהודה. shloshim v'shisha ish mamash divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's רבי
יהודה says. אמר לו רבי נחמיה Amar lo Rabbi Nechemia וכי שלושים
וששה היו? v'chi shloshim v'shisha hayu? Really? It's not literally, ולא נאמר
אלא כשלושים וששה איש. v'lo ne'emar ela kishloshim v'shisha ish. אלא זה
יאיר בן מנשה ששקול כנגד רובה של סנהדרין. Ela zeh Yair bin
Menashe sheshakul k'neged ruba shel Sanhedrin. It was one person יאיר בן
מנשה, Yair bin Menashe, you know, it's we have stories about him,
you know, at the end of במדבר. Bamidbar. Anyway, he was worth
the thirty-six of סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So to some degree it's picking up
on the כ, kaf, I don't know why we're identifying יאיר בן
מנשה, Yair bin Menashe, but the other thing it's also doing is
it's also trying to address part of the problem of it. By
making it one person and not thirty-six people, okay it's one innocent
life, it's not I mean it's still one innocent life, one innocent
life, but you know that's also a way of like maybe moderating
it a little bit, modulating it a little bit. אלא זה Ela
zeh fine. אמר רב נחמן אמר רב Amar Rav Nachman amar Rav
מאי דכתיב mai dichtiv what's meant by the פסוק pasuk תחנונים ידבר
רש ועשיר יענה עזות? tachanunim yedaber rash v'ashir ya'aneh azut? So a
supplication a poor person will speak but a rich person will speak
harshly. תחנונים ידבר רש זה משה Tachanunim yedaber rash zeh Moshe ועשיר
יענה עזות זה יהושע. v'ashir ya'aneh azut zeh Yehoshua. Okay so משה
Moshe spoke maybe he's the רש rash because he's ענו מכל אדם.
anav mikol adam. He spoke, you know, he spoke softly to God
and יהושע Yehoshua spoke harshly to God based on the מדרש midrash
that we just put these words into יהושע's Yehoshua mouth. Okay. But
actually it's not just that, we're going to quote a פסוק pasuk
in a minute, okay,
we'll see in the פסוק. pasuk תחנונים זה משה ועשיר זה יהושע.
Tachanunim zeh Moshe v'ashir zeh Yehoshua. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama אילימא משום
דכתיב eilima mishum dichtiv where do you see this difference about how
משה Moshe spoke and about how יהושע Yehoshua spoke? If it's because
it says ויצקם לפני ה' vayatzikum lifnei Hashem ואמר רב נחמן בא
וחבטם לפני המקום v'amar Rav Nachman ba v'chavtam lifnei HaMakom and that
we read into the פסוק pasuk that יהושע Yehoshua slammed them before
God. אטו פנחס לא עביד הכי? Atu Pinchas lo avid hachi? So
פנחס Pinchas did something similar. ויעמד פנחס ויפלל, Vaya'amod Pinchas vayifaleil, פנחס
Pinchas stood up and he prayed ותעצר המגפה vatatzer hamageifah and the
plague stopped. ואמר רבי אלעזר ויפלל לא נאמר V'amar Rabbi Elazar vayifaleil
lo ne'emar it didn't say he prayed which is the התפלל hitpaleil
form אלא ויפלל. ela vayifaleil. What's the,
what's the קל kal form? מלמד שעשה פלילות עם קונו. Melameid she'asah
plilot im kono. He did judgment with God. He held God to
task. Like פלילים plilim are judges. So ויפלל vayifaleil is he judged.
Right, actually Hirsch says the word תפילה tefillah the התפלל hitpaleil form
is because the process of prayer is one of judging yourself. Right,
you know, holding up yourself and how, you know. But here it's
not the התפלל hitpaleil form so he held God to task. Okay.
עם קונו בא וחבטם לפני המקום על פניו ואמר רבונו של עולם
אלו יפלו עשרים וארבעה אלף מישראל? im kono ba v'chavtam lifnei HaMakom
al panav v'amar Ribono Shel Olam elu yiplu esrim v'arba'ah elef miYisrael?
In the case of פנחס Pinchas twenty-four thousand people died and פנחס
Pinchas held God to task. דכתיב ויהיו המתים במגפה ארבעה ועשרים אלף.
Dichtiv vayihyu hametim bamageifah arba'ah v'esrim elef. Okay so okay maybe he
was, maybe משה Moshe didn't do it but, you know, יהושע Yehoshua
wasn't the only one who challenged God like this. ואלא מהכא V'ela
mei'hacha from here למה העברת העביר את העם הזה את הירדן? lamah
he'evarta ha'avir et ha'am hazeh et haYarden? Right after, you know, יהושע
Yehoshua says to God, God if you were going to kill us,
you know, you're going to have us die in battle, why did
we come into this land in the first place? So משה נמי
מימר אמר למה הרעות לעם הזה? Moshe nami meimar amar lamah harei'ota
la'am hazeh? Why did you deal harshly with this people? Okay. אלא
מהכא Ela mei'hacha ולו הואלנו ונשב בעבר הירדן. v'lu ho'alnu v'neieshev b'eiver
haYarden. It wasn't just challenging God, it was saying had we only
not crossed the Jordan river. Okay. It's funny like that's almost him
being like wistful, not so much attacking God but almost like rejecting
what God has done. Right, had we only we would have been
better off. Okay and now we don't have something like that by
משה. Moshe. Like sort of like what בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael said,
oh we should have never left מצרים. Mitzrayim. Right, right. Okay but
now moving on. ויאמר ה' אל יהושע קום לך. Vayomer Hashem el
Yehoshua kum lach. So now, you know, God says this we're back
to where God says to יהושע Yehoshua your people, you know, you
know the people have sinned and יהושע Yehoshua falls on his face
and God says to יהושע Yehoshua get up. All right, gotta deal
with it. דרש שילא אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא שלך קשה משלהם.
Darash Shila amar lei HaKadosh Baruch Hu shelcha kasha mishelahem. You know,
so what you did was worse than what they did. Hold on
let me just make sure. שלך. Shelcha. Oh right, I'm sorry. שלך.
Shelcha. Thank you. All right I'm sorry.
Right, one minute just check רש״י Rashi *Rashi* here.
Yeah, so what was... I'm just not exactly... anyway, but anyway שלך
*she-le-kha* what is of yours, you know, your responsibility that brought about...
it wasn't the people, they died in the עי *Ai* not just
because of the sin of עכן *Achan*. They died in the עי
*Ai* because of your sin as well. So that that is משלך
*mi-she-le-kha*, right, that that is, you know, your responsibility... your sin is
קשה *ka-sheh* was harsher in terms of bringing about this punishment משלהם
*mi-she-la-hem* that was the people's sin. The people sinned in this collective
sense of עכן *Achan*'s sin, but God says the reason these people
died in the battle also was a lot about your sin. What
sin did יהושע *Yehoshua* do that led to the people dying in
the battle? אני אמרתי והיה בעברכם את הירדן תקימו *Ani amarti ve-hayah
be-ovrechem et ha-Yarden takimu*. As soon as you pass over the ירדן
*Yarden*, you should erect the stones. ואתם רחקתם ששים מיל *Ve-atem richaktem
shishim mil*. And you waited until you got ששים מיל *shishim mil*
before you erected them at הר גריזים והר עיבל *Har Gerizim ve-Har
Eval*. Of course, of course תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says, I don't understand.
The פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk* says when you pass over and it says
you should erect them at הר גריזים והר עיבל *Har Gerizim ve-Har
Eval*. So what's יהושע *Yehoshua* supposed to do? הר גריזים והר עיבל
*Har Gerizim ve-Har Eval* weren't right after... right at the ירדן *Yarden*,
they were ששים מיל *shishim mil* away. So if you look at
תוספות *Tosafot* he says,
he says, like about... I have to do because the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*
also, ואתם רחקתם *ve-atem richaktem*, it's about ten lines from the end
of the תוספות *Tosafot*, line starts with היו *hayu*, it says ובירושלמי
*u-ba-Yerushalmi*. See that what it says ובירושלמי *u-ba-Yerushalmi*? So it says ובירושלמי
אמר *u-ba-Yerushalmi amar*, מה מקיים רבי אלעזר הר גריזים והר עיבל *ma-m’kayyen
Rabbi Elazar Har Gerizim ve-Har Eval*? So if you say you did
it right after... so there's a debate of תנאים *Tanna'im* in the
ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*. One says no, that they were supposed to, you know,
erect them right as soon as they passed over the ירדן *Yarden*.
Okay, but the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* says הר גריזים והר עיבל *Har
Gerizim ve-Har Eval*. So he answers, מה מקיים רבי אלעזר הר גריזים
והר עיבל *ma-m’kayyen Rabbi Elazar Har Gerizim ve-Har Eval*, דעשו שושי דעפרא
*de-asu shushi de-afra*. They made two little mounds of dirt. וקראו לאחת
הר גריזים ולאחת הר עיבל *ve-karu l’achat Har Gerizim u-l’achat Har Eval*.
So the פסוק *Pasuk* said right after, it said הר גריזים, but
we’ll make a little הר גריזים והר עיבל *Har Gerizim ve-Har Eval*
right here. And that's what they did. So that's what... and that's
what they were supposed to do. Now דאיתא רבי יהודה *d'aitat Rabbi
Yehuda*, and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says no, no, no, they did
it at the real הר גריזים והר עיבל *Har Gerizim ve-Har Eval*
and that was... they were supposed to do. So ששים מיל הלכו
באותו היום *shishim mil halchu be-oto ha-yom*. So it was when you
just pass over the ירדן *Yarden*, because they managed to traverse that
distance in ששים מיל *shishim mil* in one day. So according to
the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* there are two approaches, but either way יהושע *Yehoshua*
did the right thing. According to one approach he did it right
after the ירדן *Yarden* and he made these two little mounds, and
according to the other approach he did it at the real הר
גריזים והר עיבל *Har Gerizim ve-Har Eval* but they got there in
one day. Okay, so תוספות *Tosafot* says, אל דעתיה דרבי אלעזר לא
זזו ממקומן *al da'atei de-Rabbi Elazar lo zazu mi-mekoman*. According to רבי
אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*, they didn't move from their place, it was right
there. Now והשתא רב שילא דהכא *ve-hashta Rav Shila de-hacha*. Now רב
שילא *Rav Shila* says that they did the wrong thing. So תוספות
*Tosafot* says he's going to have to hold the... the combination of
the two positions. Okay, סבר דקרא כרבי אלעזר *savar de-kra ke-Rabbi Elazar*.
The פסוקים psukim. *Psukim* were like... meant like רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*.
They should have done it right after they got out of the
ירדן *Yarden* and they should have made these two little mounds. Okay,
והיה לו ליהושע לעשות כן *ve-hayu lo le-Yehoshua la-asot ken*. He should
have made two little mounds. But he, והוא הלך להר גריזים והר
עיבל *ve-hu halach le-Har Gerizim ve-Har Eval*. He went to the real
הר גריזים והר עיבל *Har Gerizim ve-Har Eval*. Okay, ורב דאמר דהכא
דיהושע שפיר עבד *ve-Rav d'amar de-hacha de-Yehoshua shapir avad*. He could hold
like those other opinions. But there's really a problem in the פסוקים
*Psukim*. It says when you pass over, and obviously the פשט *pshat*
could be, I think the פשט *pshat* would be, not the second
you pass over, when you pass over and get to הר גריזים
והר עיבל *Har Gerizim ve-Har Eval*, right? But anyway, the גמרא *Gemara*
here is holding יהושע *Yehoshua* responsible. Okay, so where was I?
Whole 'nother situation.
I know, I know. Okay.
So which one explains...
Right. Well also then we have to somehow deal with like this
point about, you know, did everybody... did they die just for this
one little sin? Of course it's still other people dying for a
different person's sin or whatever. Okay. ואוקים רב אמורא עליה ודרש *ve-ukim
Rav amora aleih ve-darash*. So ואוקים רב *ve-ukim Rav*, בתר דנפק *batra
de-nafak*, after whoever this... who was this that said this... רב שילא
*Rav Shila*, after רב
שילא *Rav Shila* left, רב *Rav* got an אמורא *Amora* to come
up and אמורא *Amora*'s like an announcer, and he explicated the following
way. כאשר צוה ה׳ את משה עבדו כן צוה משה את יהושע
וכן עשה יהושע *ka'asher tzivah Hashem et Moshe avdo ken tzivah Moshe
et Yehoshua ve-chen asah Yehoshua*. It's a פסוק *Pasuk* where we see
לא הסיר דבר מכל אשר צוה ה׳ את משה *lo he-sir davar
mi-kol asher tzivah Hashem et Moshe*. יהושע *Yehoshua* did exactly what he
was supposed to do. How he rejected that דרשה drasha *drasha*. You
cannot say יהושע *Yehoshua* sinned in that way to violate what God
had said. Okay. So he says אם כן מה תלמוד לומר קום
לך *im ken mah talmud lomar kum lach*? What does it mean
קום לך *kum lach*? That he's being held partly responsible for the
punishment. So אמר ליה אתה גרמת להם *amar lei attah geramta lahem*.
You brought it about. How did you bring it about? Meaning not
because you transgressed something, but your actions or inactions contributed to this.
Okay, so where... I lost my place. אתה גרמת להם *attah
geramta lahem*. והיינו דקאמר ליה ועי *ve-haynu de-ka'mar lei ve-Ai* because as
רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says what's not explicit in the גמרא *Gemara* but
רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says, you shouldn't have made the booty of יריחו
Yericho *Yericho*, you shouldn't have put it under the חרם cherem. *herem*,
right? You created the חרם cherem *herem* which then created the problem.
So who asked you to make it... put it under the חרם
cherem *herem*? Okay, והיינו דקאמר ליה ועי *ve-haynu de-ka'mar lei ve-Ai*, so
that's why God says to
him and עי *Ai*, ועשית *va-asita*. you should do for עי and
its king what you did to יריחו Yericho and its king and
so it's very funny because וגומר v'gomer because sometimes the proof of
the פסוק is in is at the end of the פסוק which
isn't quoted. The end of the פסוק is except don't put the
stuff under the חרם. So after the people fell in העי Ha'Ai
and it was because of the sin I mean it's a good
it's a very you know powerful lead to the פסוקים. The people
fell in העי Ha'Ai it was because of the sin of being
מועל בחרם moel b'cherem then after they conquered העי Ha'Ai God says
don't put this under the חרם right? Which is sort of like
you know you shouldn't have put the other one under the חרם
either. We've learned our lesson you should have learned your lesson. Okay.
Now ויהי בהיות יהושע ביריחו vayehi bihyot Yehoshua b'Yericho now when יהושע
was in יריחו Yericho now we're going back a little bit before
before העי Ha'Ai יריחו Yericho. was an earlier battle. וישא עיניו וירא
vayisa einav vayar he lifted up his eyes and he saw that
there was this person איש עומד לנגדו ish omed l'negdo ויאמר vayomer
and he said who are you הלנו אתה אם לצרינו halanu atah
im l'tzareinu are you for us or are you from the enemy?
And he said ויאמר לא כי אני שר צבא השם עתה באתי
vayomer lo ki ani sar tzeva Hashem atah bati not a person
I'm an angel of God I have come now. This was when
they were encamped against יריחו. Yericho Okay. So ויפול יהושע על פניו
ארצה וישתחו vayipol Yehoshua al panav artzah vayishtachu he fell down he
prostrated himself. היכי עביד הכי heichi avid hachi how did he do
this? So אמר רבי יוחנן אסור לו לאדם שיתן שלום לחברו בלילה
amar Rabbi Yochanan asur lo l'adam she'yiten shalom l'chavero balailah you can't
greet somebody at night you know falling on his face is and
praying is in worshipping but it's greeting somebody okay and you can't
greet them by saying שלום shalom because שלום shalom is a name
of God. חיישינן שמא שד הוא chaishinan shema shed hu he might
be a demon and you can't put God's name on a demon
so presumably this prostrating anyway would be inappropriate if this was a
demon and how could he tell if it was
nighttime? Okay תוספות said this would only apply out in the fields
where there are demons and wouldn't apply in the town. What does
it mean you see somebody in the street at night you can't
say hello? Anyway שאני התם דקאמר ליה אני שר צבא השם עתה
באתי shani hatam d'ka'amar lei ani sar tzeva Hashem atah bati by
announcing that he was an angel of God he said he wasn't
a demon. So the גמרא says ודלמא משקרי v'dilma meshakrei so maybe
he was a demon who was lying? No גמירי דלא מפקי שם
שמים לבטלה gemiri d'lo mafkei shem shamayim l'vatalah we have a tradition
that demons will not say God's name you know will not say
God's name so if he's sort of anybody who says אני שר
צבא השם ani sar tzeva Hashem I mean maybe he's a person
but he's not a demon. He's either a person or an angel.
Okay אמר ליה now what did the angel say to him? Now
that we're dealing with יהושע's responsibility. אמש ביטלתם תמיד של בין הערבים
emesh bitaltem tamid shel bein ha'arbayim last night you were you sinned
not last night actually רש״י says it actually means this is nighttime
it means right before nightfall. אמש emesh usually means the night before
but רש״י says it means like right before nightfall you didn't you
were so busy in your encampment that you didn't bring the קרבן
korban you were supposed to bring. Okay meaning so you're allowing your
encampment of יריחו to compromise your religious responsibilities. ועכשיו ביטלתם תלמוד תורה
v'achshav bitaltem Talmud Torah now you're maintaining the siege at night you
know nobody's going anywhere at night. So do some learning now. Don't
be working on the siege. So he said על איזה מהן באת
al eizeh mehen bata so which one am I being punished for?
Which one made you come? אמר ליה עתה באתי amar lei atah
bati now the תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah the ביטול תלמוד תורה bittul
Talmud Torah that was the bigger sin. מיד וילן יהושע בלילה ההוא
miyad vayalen Yehoshua balailah hahu he slept that night בתוך העמק b'toch
ha'emek in the valley ואמר רבי יוחנן מלמד שלן בעומקה של הלכה
v'amar Rabbi Yochanan melamed she'lan b'umkah shel halachah he said okay that's
what we're giving שיעור. shiur. All right. So he corrected it and
he had everybody engaging that night in the depths of learning. Okay.
אמר רב שמואל בר אוניא משמיה דרב גדול תלמוד תורה יותר מהקרבת
תמידים amar Rav Shmuel bar Unya mishmei d'Rav gadol Talmud Torah yoter
me'hakravat temidim תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is greater than the bringing of
daily sacrifices שנאמר עתה באתי she'ne'emar atah bati pretty explicit in the
implicit in what we just said. אמר ליה אביי לרב דימי האי
קרא במערבא במאי מוקמיתו ליה amar lei Abaye l'Rav Dimi hai kra
b'ma'arava b'mai mokmitu lei what do you do with this פסוק in
ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? אל תצא לריב מהר פן מה תעשה באחריתה
al taitzei l'riv maher pen mah ta'aseh b'acharitah don't quickly go get
into a debate an argument quickly because you don't know what you'll
do with the outcome of it בהכלים אותך רעך b'hachlim otcha re'echa
when your when you're you don't know how you know you're going
to get into a fight and then you'll be embarrassed by your
friend. ריבך ריב את רעך rivcha riv et re'echa fight what you
need to with your friend וסוד אחר אל תגל v'sod acher al
tegal but do not reveal the secret of somebody else. All right
that's nice you know sort of like aphorism or whatever but he
understood that there was something to דרשן darshen with this or he
heard that they had a nice דרשה in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
So he said what דרש drash do you have? So he said
בשעה שאמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא ליחזקאל b'sha'ah she'amar lo HaKadosh Baruch
Hu l'Yechezkel when God said to יחזקאל Yechezkel לך אמור להם לישראל
אביכם האמורי ואמכם חתית lech emor lahem l'Yisrael avichem ha'Emori v'imchem Chittit
go tell to the people your father is an אמורי Emori and
your mother is a חתית Chittit you're doing like the sins of
the of the Canaanites you're like as if they gave birth here.
I mean so רוח פסקונית ruach paskonit this spirit of I don't
even know what the word פסקונית paskonit here the judgment spirit I
don't know how they translate it there. Anyway this type of a
רש״י says it's גבריאל Gavriel this angel but I don't know what
they say for פסקונית? paskonit? Intercessor. Intercessor? I don't know how פסקונית
paskonit means intercessor. Anyway said ריבונו של
עולם
Ribono shel
Olam master of the universe אם יבוא אברהם ושרה ויעמדו לפניך im
yavo Avraham v'Sarah v'yamdu lefanecha if אברהם Avraham and שרה Sarah were
to come and stand before You you're saying their father is a
חתית Chittit and their mother is a you know whichever it was
is a father's an אמורי Emori mother's חתית? Chittit? How would you
feel if אברהם Avraham and ושרה v'Sarah was standing right here? How
would they feel? Okay, אומר להם, Omer lahem, אתה אומר להם, atah
omer lahem, you would say this to them ומכלים אותם umachlim otam
and you would embarrass them? That's from the פסוק, you know, your
friend will embarrass you. ריבך ריב את רעך, Ribcha riv et re'acha,
if you got some complaint with בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, fine, fight
it out with them, okay, וסוד אחר אל תגל, vesod acher al
tegal, but do not reveal the secret of somebody else. Now what's
the secret? I mean the point is that in some way you
could sort of say that אברהם Avraham and שרה Sarah were Canaanites,
you know, because they came from תרח, Terach, I mean was תרח
Terach from ארם נהרים Aram Naharayim or was he from כנען, Kena'an,
you know, it's a little bit unclear, the whole רש"י רמב"ן Ramban
about that, but anyway do not embarrass other people because you're trying
to have a fight with בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. You know, state,
work out your issue with בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. Okay. ומי אית
ליה רשותא כולי האי Umi is lei reshusa koli hai does גבריאל,
Gavriel, we'll see if גבריאל Gavriel whatever, have that degree of license
to challenge God? It's also about challenging God by the way. That's
also the continued theme. Okay. אם, יש, yesh, אמר רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא, amar Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina, שלשה שמות יש לו, sheloshah shemos
yesh lo, he has three names: פסקון, Piscon, אטמון, Itmon, סיגרון. Sigron.
פסקון Piscon שפוסק דברים כלפי מעלה, sheposek devarim klapei ma'alah, he has
a right to cut words, to say harsh words before God. אטמון
Itmon שאוטם עונותיהם של ישראל, she-otem avonoseihem shel Yisrael, he closes up
their sins, he protects the Jewish people. And סיגרון, Sigron, כיון שסוגר
שוב אין פותח, kivan shesoger shuv ein pote'ach, once he closes a
topic you can't open it up anymore. Okay. Let's just get to
the two dots. I really just have two minutes. היערך שועך ולא
בצר. Haye'aroch shova'ach velo batzar. Okay, so will you play pray set
out your your your prayers not in anguish? אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar
Rabbi Elazar, לעולם יקדים אדם תפילה לצרה, le'olam yakdim adam tefillah letzarah,
you should always place out your prayers before the bad things happen.
שאלמלא הקדים אברהם תפילה לצרה בין בית אל ובין העי, she-imalai hikdim
Avraham tefillah letzarah bein Beis El uvein ha-Ai, as אברהם Avraham made
a מזבח mizbe'ach between בית אל Beis El and the Ai. So
we're back to the Ai. And the Ai is where the people
died, right? So if אברהם Avraham had not prayed there, you know,
a millennium before for the sake of ישראל, Yisrael, לא נשתייר משונאי
ישראל שריד ופליט. lo nish'ayar misonei Yisrael sarid upalit. You know, nobody
would be left, right? They would not just 36, many more would
have died. וריש לקיש אמר כל המאמץ עצמו בתפילה מלמטה אין לו
צרים מלמעלה, Verish Lakish amar kol ha-ma'amitz atzmo bitefillah milmata ein lo
tzarim milmala, he reads the פסוק differently. If your heart, work hard
on your prayer, nobody up in heaven will complain against you. ויוחנן
אמר לעולם יבקש אדם רחמים שיהו הכל מאמיצות כחו, Ve-Yochanan amar le'olam
yivakesh adam rachamim she-yehu kol ma'amitzos kocho, you should always pray that
up in heaven everybody should strengthen you ואל יהיו לו צרים מלמעלה
ve-al yehu lo tzarim milmala and nobody should be working against you.
Okay, we have to end here.